اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله رَبِّ الّعَالَمِيْن ۝الرَّحْمَنِ الرَّحِيمِ ۝ مَالِكِ يَوْمِ الدِّينِ۝
وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِ الأَّوَلِيْن والْآخرين محمد إبن عبدالله
وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
أمَّا بَعدْ
نَسْعل الله ألعظيم أن يبارك لنا في جمعنا هذا
أللهم يا ذالجمال والكمال والإكرام
أن ينفعنا بما علمتنا
وعلِّمْنَا مِمَّا ينفعنا ، وزدنا علمًا
أللهمَّ جعل هذالقاء خالص الِوَجه الْكَريْم
ولَتَجعل لِأحدٍ فِيْه نَصِيْبَا
أللهم إنَّا نسْعَلُك إخْلَاصَ في القولي والعمل
ربنا آتنا في الدنيا حسنتًا وَ في الْآخرة حسنتًا وقِنا عَذابً النَّار۝
Dear brothers, this is an Islamic study course.
And we'll be studying a classical book.
This book was written by Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس), in the ninth, Hijri(هجري) century.
So that's the 14th century, in the Gregorian calendar.
So it's an old book.
It would be therefore 600 years old.
That's when the book was written.
Now the book is exclusively on the topic of Jihad(جهاد).
And why are we talking about such a topic?
Number one, because this is an integral part of Fiqh(فقه).
Open any book of Fiqh(فقه) you would find, Kitab Al-Jihad(كتاب الجهاد).
So it's part of Fiqh(فقه), it's a very important part.
However, because of the circumstances today, it has became a very obscure issue.
The issue of Jihad(جهاد) has accumulated many misinterpretations, many confusions.
So, even though it's such an important principle, but it's not clear in the minds of everyone.
When I say everyone, I'm meaning Muslims.
And that's why we want to go and study an old book rather than a new one.
Because with the salaf(سلف), the old Muslims, most likely they would have it right, unlike Khalaf(خلف),
who among them, you would find an accumulation of different influences.
Now, I want to state in the beginning and make it very clear
that our study of this book is not an exhortation or an invitation to violence,
or promotion of violence against an individual or a society or a state.
This is purely an academic study.
We're studying a book that is 600 years old, written by one of the Ulama(علماء) of Salaf(سلف).
So that is the extent of what we're doing.
It's a purely academic study of an old traditional book.
The book itself is written in the way that was followed by our old scholars
and that is the chapter would start by Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an relating to the topic,
and then it would go on to mention the Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and then he may quote some of the statements of the scholars.
So the comments of Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) himself in the book are very few and far in between.
However, whenever he does make a comment,
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), his comments are very concise and to the point.
And his writings in the book are really fabulous,
whenever you get to find his writings.
Because the way of the Salaf(سلف), is  it's mostly a compilation, it's Daleel(دلیل) based.
So they would have the Ayah(آية) of Qur'an, the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
then they might quote the opinion of a scholar here and there.
The author himself, let's talk about the author Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس).
His name is Ahmad Ibn Ibrahim(أحمدإبن إبراهيم) Ibn Muhammad(إبن محمد) Al-Dimishqi Al-Dimyati(ألدمشقي ألدمياطي),
Dimishqi(دمشقي) from Dimishq(دمشق),
Dimiyati(دمياطي) from Dimiyat(دمياط), in Egypt.
So our earliest scholars, they would start with their land of birth.
And then if they move anywhere, they would attribute themselves to that place.
It's not like they had to wait for five years, until they get a citizenship or so.
Immediately, he moves to a place, he likes that he considers to be his home
he attributes himself to that place.
So originally his he's a Syrian from Damascus.
But because he settled in Egypt,
and the reason why he has left from Syria,
is he was upset with the people, because they were not fighting Jihad(جهاد) as he considered appropriately.
So he went out and went to Egypt and he settled in Alexandria,
so that he could be close to the land of Ribat(رباط) at the time.
Because that was a front, with the Romans, the Romans would attack by sea,
they would attack Alexandria.
So that's where he based himself, in Dimiyat(دمياط).
In those days, a Muslim can travel from one corner of the Muslim world to the other,
you could start out from the extreme east, the borders with China.
And then you can travel through Khurasan(خراسان) and go to Kabul.
and then you go to Baghdad,
and then you go from Baghdad to Damascus,
and then to Jerusalem
and then you go to Makkah and Madina,
and then you go to San'aa(صنعاء) in Yemen
and then you go to Cairo,
in Egypt and then to Alexandria,
and then you move on to Al-Kairouan(ألقيروان) in Tunis(تيونس),
and then you go to Fas(فاس) in Morocco
and then you go up north to Spain to Qurtaba(قرطبة).
And the only two identifications that you need is
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُولَ الله
No passport, no photo ID's, nothing!
So you can travel from one corner to the other.
And these are the only two identifications you need.
So there's one Orientalist, he is a professor at the University of Chicago.
He says that, it's very rare to find among the old Muslim scholars,
anyone who wasn't the seasoned traveler they've been all over.
Because traveling broadens the horizon,
it opens up the mind, it gives you experience.
As-Sakhawi(ألسخاوي), he says about Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس),
he was eager to do good, preferred living in obscurity.
You know, he had that Zuhd(زهد) and Khamool(خمول),
he hated the fame and being in the spotlight,
showed no arrogance or pride, due to his knowledge.
Whoever would see him would think he is a commoner.
You don't see any special dress code or a big Amama(عمامة) or
anything to point out that he is different, that he is a scholar.
He looked like a commoner.
Although a handsome man with a beautiful beard,
short and medium built,
spent a lot of his life stationed in Jihad(جهاد),
until he died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
So the author of this book is a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
And after he finished the book,
as soon as he finish the book, nine months later, he died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد)
in one of the attacks of the Romans, on a coastal town in Egypt.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) as Syed Qutub(سيد قطب) says, our words are dead,
until we give them life with our blood.
So the book of Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) is considered to be the best book on Jihad(جهاد).
Because it's written by a man who lived it.
It's written by a man who experienced it.
And it's written by a man whose actions were, an exact replica of his words.
He practiced what he preached, he walked the talk.
Ibn ul Aamad(ابن العماد), he says,
The Shaikh(شيخ) - The Imam(اِمَام), - The scholar - And The exampler.
In 814, Hijri(هجري), the Romans attack the people of At-Teena(الطینة) in Egypt.
The people of the Dimyat(دمياط), led by Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس),
went to join their brothers in their fight against the invading forces, and he died in the battlefield.
Tayeb(طيب) I'll read through the table of contents to the book.
So you'll get an understanding of what the book is talking about.
CHAPTER ONE,
On the command of Jihad(جهاد) against the non-believers and its mandate
and the stern warning against those who don't practice Jihad(جهاد).
CHAPTER TWO,
The virtues of Jihad(جهاد) and Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
So in this chapter he talks about the virtues.
The virtues of Jihad(جهاد).
Jihad(جهاد) is the best deed after Salah(صلاة) and being dutiful towards ones parents.
Jihad(جهاد) is the greatest deed after believing in Allah.
Jihad(جهاد) is greater than worshiping in the house of Allah and serving it and serving the pilgrims.
References that Jihad(جهاد) is the greatest deed of all.
Jihad(جهاد) is the most beloved deed to Allah.
The Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is the greatest of all people.
No one can practice any act of worship equivalent to Jihad(جهاد),
references that the sleep of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than the praying of the night
and fasting of the day for others.
Allah reserved 100 levels in paradise for the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
between each level and the other is the distance between the heavens and Earth.
The Rahbania(رهبانیة) and Siaha(سیاحة) of this nation is Jihad(جهاد),
the pinnacle of Islam is Jihad(جهاد),
the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is given a guarantee By Allah,
Allah will never forsake the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) but would help them and respond to their prayers,
miscellaneous rewards of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
references to the preference of Jihad(جهاد) over Hajj(حَجْ),
the virtues of encouraging Jihad(جهاد),
the virtue of racing towards Jihad(جهاد),
the virtues of the dust in the Path Allah,
the virtues of riding the sea in Jihad(جهاد),
the virtues of horses and keeping them for the purpose of Jihad(جهاد),
the virtue of fear in the path of Allah,
the virtues of standing in the ranks on the battlefield,
a chapter on the farewell of the fighters.
CHAPTER THREE,
the virtues of spending in the cause of Allah,
the punishment of withholding wealth from being spent in the path of Allah,
the virtues of providing for the fighters in the path of Allah, and taking care of their families.
CHAPTER FOUR,
the virtues of Ribat(رباط),
and the virtues of the one, who dies in Ribat(رباط), and then it talks about the period of being stationed,
the virtues of guarding in the path of Allah.
CHAPTER FIVE,
the rules and virtues of target shooting.
It talks about the virtues of target shooting,
rules of betting,
on racing and target shooting,
rules of betting, on target shooting.
the warning against whoever learns shooting and then deserts it.
and the virtues of swords.
CHAPTER SIX
the virtue of injury in the sake of Allah,
CHAPTER SEVEN
the virtues of killing a non believer for the sake of Allah.
CHAPTER EIGHT,
the virtue of an individual or a small group,
immersing themselves within a large army of non believers in search of martyrdom,
and causing damage to the enemy.
CHAPTER NINE, on dueling.
CHAPTER TEN,
The severe punishment for the one, who turns his back during battle.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
on the intentions in Jihad(جهاد)
and he talks about the different intentions in Jihad(جهاد)
the pleasure of Allah
love for Islam
seeking paradise, self defense,
both Jihad(جهاد) and booties,
booty recognition,
rulings on being paid for fighting
seeking recognition in Jihad(جهاد) after starting it with a sincere intention,
the ruling of the one, who boasts about his Jihad(جهاد),
and Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) who goes on Jihad(جهاد) and dies without fighting is a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
CHAPTER TWELVE,
Martyrdom.
He talks about asking for martyrdom and getting it,
the virtues of martyrdom.
The earth does not consume the bodies of the martyrs
and then the virtues of martyrs and He mentioned 17 different virtues.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN:
The rulings regarding Muslim POW's
CHAPTER FORTEEN:
the history of Jihad(جهاد).
He talks about in the time of Rasool Ullah, and then after that.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN,
courage and fear.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN,
necessary rulings for the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) to know,
he talks about Ghanimah(غنيمه), - Galol(غلول), Salb(سلب),
POW’s,
whether they're Muslim, or the enemy POW's,
And then CHAPTER 17,
a brief chapter on the art of war.
So it's a pretty comprehensive book.
How will we study this book, we'll do it
the traditional way of Halaqaat(حلقات).
I'll read through the book, just read it word, by word.
and if there's any comments, I'll comment on it.
And if you have any questions then you could raise those questions,
so it's not going to be a lecture style.
We're going to be reading through the book.
And this is the Tahzeeb(تهذيب) of the book.
The book itself is pretty big.
It's two volumes.
Yeah, that's the first volume and the second volume is the same size.
I did a Tahzeeb(تهذيب) of it.
And halfway through, I found out that there is already a Tahzeeb(تهذيب) in Arabic done
by Professor Sulah Abdul Fattah Al-Khalidi(صلاح عبدالفتاح ألخالدي),
- he is a professor in the Jordanian University.
And it's a good, it's a pretty good Tahzeeb(تهذيب).
Now when we say Tahzeeb(تهذيب).
The book does have some weak Ahadith(احاديث) and maybe some fabricated Hadith(حديث),
And he also talks about a lot of stories, and Karamat(کرامات).
Some of them are without the Sanad(سند).
So what I did in Tahzeeb(تهذيب), the half which I did was?
I took out all of the weak and fabricated Ahadith(احاديث),
and some of the stories and Karamat(کرامات) that do not have a Sanad(سند)
and left the ones that seem to be reasonable.
And I also took out things that are not necessarily relevant to our context today.
For example, he talks a lot about horses, he talks a lot about swords,
I abbreviated those chapters.
And then for the other half after I found out about this arabic Tahzeeb(تهذيب),
I just did a translation of that.
And he follows the same rules.
So we're actually reading Tahzeeb(تهذيب) of the book,
but In sha Allah(إن شاءالله) we're not losing anything from the original.
In terms of anything that's authentic.
Everything that is authentic, was retained.
Before we start with the book,
I think it's necessary to talk about some definitions and background, an intro,
What's the definition of Jihad(جهاد)?
Because the concept has become quite confused now.
It's necessary to do some study on the definition of what it means.
And I'm sure that you would benefit from this in terms of your discussion with people,
who might not have a clear understanding of what Jihad(جهاد) means.
Now any word would have a linguistic meaning,
every word has a linguistic meaning and this is when the word was originally formed, it was formed to mean something.
For example horse,
horse has a linguistic meaning and it is the animal which we call horse,
that is the linguistic meaning of the word.
But then you have words in Arabic would pick up what is called the Sharie(شرعي) meaning,
a meaning of Sharia(شريعة).
And this is a meaning that is new,
that is given to the word by who?
By Islam!
For example, Salah(صلاة) is a word that was known to the Arabs before Islam,
What did it mean?
To meant?
What does it mean?
Dua(دُعَا)…
The meaning the linguistic meaning of Salah(صلاة) in Arabic is Dua(دُعَا).
Islam came and gave Salah(صلاة) a completely new meaning,
which is defined by ulama(علماء)
الافعال و القوال التی بین التکبیر و التسلیم
Salah(صلاة) is the actions and the words that are done between the Takbeer(تكبير) and the Salam(سلام).
So that is called Salah(صلاة).
This is a new meaning that was introduced by Islam.
And then you have Ma'ana Urfi(معنی عرفی).
Urfi(عرفي) is customary.
So word would have a linguisticmeaning but over time,
people will start using that word to mean something else.
And eventually the word will forget about its linguistic meaning.
For example, in English,
excuse me for choosing this word.
This is the only word I could come up with, I did this tahzeeb(تهذيب) very fast today,
the word gay.
Gay in English linguistically means
happy...
Pleasant
It also means brave.
These are the linguistic meanings of the word.
But if you mentioned this word today, no one will recall these meanings,
their minds will immediately go to homosexuals.
So the words picked up some customary meanings
and these customary meanings became the
Meaning understood by the listener when the word is used.
You don't go around and telling people that I'm gay,
and you want to say that you're brave or happy,
you don't do that anymore.
So this is the customary meaning that is given to the word.
And then a word has a Ma'ana Istalahi(معنی اصطلاحی).
Istalahi (اصطلاحی) means technical.
So, among a certain group the word would have a specific meaning.
So for example, the word minister in English.
Among politicians would mean something different than among religious groups
In a religious group a minister is the one, who's in the church who administers the prayers and all of that,
he is called minister.
But in this country
in the political arena, a minister is head of a government department.
And in some countries he would be the .... what is called in America the secretary.
So the Secretary of State will be the Minister of State.
So this is a technical meaning,
the technical meaning changes from one group to another
or it could be the same.
So these are the four meanings of the word.
And then you have a fifth and that is Majaz(مجاز).
A word could be used, could be borrowed to signify a different meaning and that is figurative speech,
it is figurative speech.
You don't need it literally, you are borrowing the word for another meaning.
Tayeb(طیب), what is the linguistic meaning of a Jihad(جهاد),
The Sharie(شرعي) meaning of Jihad(جهاد),
the Technical meanings
and the customary meaning.
To give you an example of Majaz(مجاز) before we go into Jihad(جهاد).
A man came to Muhammadﷺ and said:
O Rasool Ullah, Do I still have a duty towards my parents
after they die?
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes!
You make Salah(صلاة) on them
and then you make Istaghfar(إستغفار) for them
and you fulfill their promises to others
and you are generous towards their friends
and you fulfill their kinship.
But the point here is that Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
You make Salah(صلاة) on your parents.
Does Rasool Allah ﷺ means the Sharie(شرعي) meaning of Salah(صلاة)?
The religious meaning of Salah(صلاة)? No!
What the Rasool Ullah mean here?
The linguistic meaning!
So, this is Majaz(مجاز).
Over here Salah(صلاة) is used in Majaz(مجاز) sense
because Salah(صلاة) has already been given a new meaning by Islam,
you can't use it in linguistic meaning.
Whenever Salah(صلاة) is now used for the linguistic meaning it's used in a Majaz(مجاز) sense,
it is used in a figurative sense.
So, Rasul Ullah is figuratively, saying that you make Salah(صلاة) on them,
which means you make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
Tayeb(طيب), what is the linguistic meaning Jihad(جهاد)?
Jihad(جهاد) is the word that existed before Islam.
It is not a word invented by Islam,
so the linguistic meaning of it,
according to lisaan-Ul-Arab(لسان العرب) which is, an authority in the Arabic language.
استفراغ ما فی الوسع و الطاقة من قول و عمل
Jihad(جهاد) means exhausting your efforts in a deed or word.
You exhaust your effort,
you go to the limit,
do your best in a deed or work.
So this is a very general meaning.
You could be exhausting your effort for Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)
or you could be exhausting effort for Allah that’s all Jihad(جهاد).
According to the linguistic meaning.
So linguistically Jihad(جهاد) is struggling and striving for anything.
It can be striving for money,
striving to marry,
striving to fight the Kuffar(كفار) or
striving to fight with Momineen(مؤمنين) it’s all Jihad(جهاد) in a linguistic sense.
Now Shariah(شريعة) introduced a new meaning of Jihad(جهاد),
and what is that meaning?
According to Hashia Ibn Abideen(حاشیة ابن عابدین)
which is a Hanafi(حنفي) book of Fiqh(فقه).
بذل الوسعي في القتال في سبيل الله
مباشرةً أو معاونتًا بمالٍ أو راْيٍ
أو تَكثيْر سوادٍ أو غَير ذالك
In Hashia Ibn Abideen(حاشیة ابن عابدین) the definition of Jihad(جهاد) is the following.
Striving to the limit,
in fighting in the sake of Allah directly,
or by money,
or intellect,
or by increasing the numbers
or other means,
and in the commentary, it says that other means could be tending to the injured
or preparing food.
So according to this definition it includes the direct fighting,
but it also includes the indirect means
of supporting by money
or by intellect, your opinion,
or by cooking food or by attending to the injured.
But when we're saying indirectly here, the intention must be for that cause.
And it must be a deed that relates.
So you can't for example, say that
Oh, I'm working as a an engineer and that's you know,
there must be some link for it, to serve the Qital(قتال),
for it to be included in Jihad(جهاد).
So therefore Jihad(جهاد) is more general term than Qital(قتال).
Qital(قتال) is specific, Qital(قتال) is the Actual fighting.
Jihad(جهاد) is more comprehensive.
Jihad(جهاد) includes Qital(قتال) and everything that is supportive of Qital(قتال).
Because Qital(قتال) doesn't stand alone.
There's a huge infrastructure that helps it
and sometimes that infrastructure is manned by more people than the actual fighters.
The financial infrastructure, the supportive infrastructure, the intellectual infrastructure
but all that is within Jihad(جهاد).
Now this meaning only came about in Madina,
it wasn't in Makkah.
This meaning came in Madina.
The word Jihad(جهاد) is mentioned in Makkah in four Ayaat(آيات).
These Ayaat(آيات) are
Al-Ankaboot (ألعنكبوت) Verse 6,8, and 69.
Plus one Ayah(آية) in Surah Luqman(سورة لقمان) verse 15,
The Ayaat(آيات) in Surah Al-Ankaboot(سورةالعنکبوت)
وَمَن جَٰهَدَ فَإِنَّمَا يُجَٰهِدُ لِنَفْسِهِۦٓ ۚ
And whoever strives, he strives only for himself.
The Second Ayah(آية)
وَإِن جَاهَدَاكَ عَلَىٰ أَن تُشْرِكَ بِي مَا لَيْسَ لَكَ بِهِ عِلْمٌ فَلَا تُطِعْهُمَا ۖ
But if they strive to make you join with Me in worship
anything as a partner of which you have no knowledge and obey them not.
So this Ayah(آية) is talking about Jihad(جهاد) that was not for the sake of Allah.
This Ayah(آية) is saying that if your parents make Jihad(جهاد) against you
to have you worship somebody besides Me, don't follow them.
So you see that in Makkah the word Jihad(جهاد) doesn't have its Shariah(شريعة) meaning yet.
It's still the linguistic meaning of the word.
The third Ayah(آية),
وَٱلَّذِينَ جَٰهَدُواْ فِينَا لَنَهْدِيَنَّهُمْ سُبُلَنَا ۚ
The ones who, make Jihad(جهاد) in My cause
We will surely guide them to Our paths.
So this is not specifically talking about fighting it's talking in the general sense.
and the Ayah(آية) in Surah Luqman(سورة لقمان)
وَإِن جَاهَدَاكَ عَلَىٰ أَن تُشْرِكَ بِي مَا لَيْسَ لَكَ بِهِ عِلْمٌ فَلَا تُطِعْهُمَا ۖ
It's the same as Ayah(آية) before a referring to the parents.
So these Ayaat(آيات) are clear.!
Tayeb(طيِّب) in Madina Jihad(جهاد) is mentioned 26 times
and invariably they are referring to fighting in the sake of Allah,
And this is final meaning of Jihad(جهاد).
I'm saying this because nowadays it is very common
to find among Muslims, the understanding
that Jihad(جهاد) is primarily Jihad An-Nafs(جهاد النفس)
and the secondary meaning is the fighting with Kuffar(كفار).
And the Hadith(حديث) is always quoted in this context:
We came back from the minor Jihad(جهاد) to Major Jihad(جهاد),
Jihad-Un-Nafs(جهاد النفس).
Now, first of all this Hadith(حديث) as Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) says, is fabricated.
Nevertheless, you will still find that this is quite a common belief.
But if we look at the Ayaat(آيات),
we'd find that the Ayah(آية) would only make sense
if Jihad(جهاد) is interpreted as fighting.
For example
the Ayah(آية) in Surah At-Tauba(سورة التوبة) Verse 41.
ٱنفِرُواْ خِفَافًا وَثِقَالًا
وَجَٰهِدُواْ بِأَمْوَٰلِكُمْ وَأَنفُسِكُمْ فِى سَبِيلِ ٱللَّهِ ۚ
March forth, whether you are light or heavy
and strive hard with your wealth and your lives, in the cause of Allah.
How come this Ayah(آية) will only make sense if it's refer to fighting.
Again the Ayah(آية), March forth
whether you are light or heavy and strive hard with your wealth and your lives in the cause of Allah.
How come it only make sense if it's refer to fighting?
Infiroo(اِنْفِرُو), the Ayah(آية) is saying March forth.
Jihad Un-Nafs(جهاد النفس) doesn't need marching forth,
the Jihad(جهاد) of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) doesn't need marching forth.
The Jihad(جهاد) of the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين) within the ranks doesn't need marching forth.
You fight them right then in neighborhood, you doesn't have to go out.
So The Ayah(آية) would only make sense
- if it is talking about the Jihad bil Kufar(جهاد بالکفار),
The next Ayah(آية)
فَرِحَ ٱلْمُخَلَّفُونَ بِمَقْعَدِهِمْ خِلَٰفَ رَسُولِ ٱللَّهِ
وَكَرِهُواْ أَن يُجَٰهِدُواْ بِأَمْوَٰلِهِمْ وَأَنفُسِهِمْ فِى سَبِيلِ ٱللَّهِ وَقَالُواْ لَا تَنفِرُواْ فِى ٱلْحَرِّ ۗ
قُلْ نَارُ جَهَنَّمَ أَشَدُّ حَرًّا ۚ لَّوْ كَانُواْ يَفْقَهُونَ۝
Those who stayed away, rejoice and they're staying behind the Messenger of Allah.
They hated to strive with their properties and their lives in the cause of Allah. And they said:
March, not forth in the heat,
say, the fire of hell is more intense in heat.
If only they could understand.
This was in the battle of Tabook(تبوك).
It was summer
It was right before the harvest, which means that thefood level at its slowest right before the harvest.
And it's about to be at its highest, if they would stay behind for harvest.
And this would be the longest journey ever
because they are going from Madina all the way to the Roman empire, Tabook(تبوك).
And its fighting with a Very formidable enemies, the Romans.
So this was a serious challenge.
This is really the test of the true Eeman(ايمان) and Nifaq(نِفاق)
that's when the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين) truly showed their color, it was in Ghazwa Tabuk(غزوة التبوك).
Because all the elements were against the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين),
the challenge was too big for them.
So they told Rasool Allah ﷺ,
these are excuses we can't go, everyone came up with an excuse.
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ left - they were happy.
فَرِحَ ٱلْمُخَلَّفُونَ
They were happy that they stayed behind, they rejoiced.
And they said: Don't go out, it's too hot.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is telling them that Jahannum(جَهَّنَّم) is hotter that the summer of Arabia.
But this Ayah(آية) can only mean,
Jihad(جهاد) - in this Ayah(آية) can only mean - going out,
and the other Ayah(آية) also in Surat Touba(سورةالتوبة) verse 86.
وَإِذَا أُنزِلَتْ سُورَةٌ أَنْ ءَامِنُواْ بِٱللَّهِ وَجَٰهِدُواْ مَعَ رَسُولِهِ
ٱسْتَـْٔذَنَكَ أُوْلُواْ ٱلطَّوْلِ مِنْهُمْ
وَقَالُواْ ذَرْنَا نَكُن مَّعَ ٱلْقَٰعِدِينَ۝
And when Surah(سورة) is revealed
enjoining them to believe in Allah and to make Jihad(جهاد) with the Messenger of Allah.
The wealthy among them ask you,
leave to exempt them and they say, leave us behind,
we would be with those who sit home.
See the wealthy are always hesitant to go.
What about the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ?
Tayeb(طيِّب)
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) says and this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(مسلم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked,
Is there any deed equivalent to Jihad(جهاد)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes!
But you won't be able to do it.
So the man asked again,
he asked the third time,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him third time.
What is equivalent to the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد),
is the one who is fasting and praying continuously.
Until the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) comes back.
How come this Hadith(حديث) is only mean fighting.
What is in this Hadith(حديث) that tells you straight away
that this can only mean fighting.
Comes back!
He came back, the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) came back.
So you're praying and fasting, until the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) comes back.
So the one who's staying behind is actually doing what??
Jihad(جهاد) of What?
Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس)!!!
The one who's staying behind praying and fasting.
He is doing Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس)..…
So Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that,
this person who is doing Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس) even if he's praying all the night, fasting everyday
is not gonna get near, to the one who goes out for Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
The next Hadith(حديث)
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked
guide me to a deed equivalent to Jihad(جهاد)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I don’t find any,
then he said:
When the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) goes on Jihad(جهاد), so now he's going,
can you enter your Masjid(مسجد) and pray continuously
and fast and never break your fast.
The man said: And who could do that.
And this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Third Hadith(حديث),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
after he was asked:
What is the best Jihad(جهاد)?
So now the question is placed straightforward to Rasul Ullah:
What's the best Jihad(جهاد).?
What's the major Jihad(جهاد)?
See sometime if you look at the Sahih Hadith(صحيح حديث)
you would find the answer.
So this Hadith(حديث),
the man is asking Rasul Ullah, what is the best Jihad(جهاد)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
من عقر جوادہ ، وأریق دمه
The ones, whose horse is killed and his blood spilled.
So that is the best Jihad(جهاد).
The ones whose horse is killed and his blood is spilled.
So this is in the context of fighting.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says that it is the best.
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) narrates that the Messenger of Allah said:
When your brothers were killed at Uhud(أحَد)
Allah placed their souls in the insides of green birds.
These birds drink from the rivers of Paradise,
and eat from its fruits, and travel in paradise wherever they want.
So they said:
We wish our people knew what Allah has given us.
- So they would desire Jihad(جهاد) and not neglect it.
So over here,
the Sahabah(صحابه) the Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء) of Uhud(أحَد) are saying in Jannah(جنة),
we wish that the pleasure that we are in, is conveyed to our people.
So they will not neglect Jihad(جهاد).
Notice here that they just said Jihad(جهاد), they didn't add a clause to it.
To define whether it is Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس) or Jihad(جهاد)…
They just said: Jihad(جهاد)
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said: I will convey that to your brothers.
So they became very pleased. And that's when Allah
revealed the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah Al-Imran(سورة ألعمران)
from Ayah(آية) Verse 169 to 171.
Talking about the Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء),
and don't consider the ones who died in the sake of Allah
as dead, but they're alive.
وَلا تَحْسَبَنَّ الَّذِينَ قُتِلُوا فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ أَمْواتًا
بَلْ أَحْياءٌ عِنْدَ رَبِّهِمْ يُرْزَقُونَ ۞
فَرِحِينَ بِمَا آتَاهُمُ اللَّهُ مِن فَضْلِهِ
وَيَسْتَبْشِرُونَ بالَّذِينَ لَمْ يَلْحَقُوا بِهِم مِّنْ خَلْفِهِمْ
أَلَّا خَوْفٌ عَلَيْهِمْ وَلَا هُمْ يَحْزَنُونَ ۞
يَسْتَبْشِرُونَ بِنِعْمَةٍ مِّنَ اللَّهِ وَفَضْلٍ وَأَنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يُضِيعُ أَجْرَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ ۞
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates that one of the companions passed by a fresh
by a spring of fresh water in the valley.
He said: If I seclude myself from the people,
and stay in this valley to worship Allah.
So this man wanted to do Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس),
stay next to this fountain of water,
devoting himself to the Ibadah(عبادة) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ full time,
stay away from the sins,
stay away from people.
But he wanted to seek permission from the Rasool Allah ﷺ first.
So he went to Rasul Ullah and he asked him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Don't do so.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
The posting of one of you in the path of Allah
is better than his prayer in his house for 70 years.
Don't you want Allah to forgive you and enter you into paradise.
Fight!
And Rasul Ullah use the word Ughoo(اُغْزوا)
in the path of Allah, for whoever fights
قاتَل
in the path of Allah,
a time equivalent to that of milking camel,
paradise is guaranteed for him.
This Hadith(حديث) is in At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ).
Tayeb(طيِّب) so that's an Hadith(حديث).
What about now let's talk about the Maana-Al-Urfi(معنی العرفی)
the customary meaning of Jihad(جهاد).
What meaning did Jihad(جهاد) pick up in the customs of people.
So now, let's say that two men are talking in the first or second century of Islam.
And one of them tells the other Jihad(جهاد).
What will the other person understand that is the customary meaning.
If we start at the time of Rasul Ullah,
the women came to Rasul Ullah and said:
they came complaining to Rasool Allah ﷺ
that  the men are praying in Jama'ah(جماعة) and they are doing what?
They're fighting Jihad(جهاد).
So the women were complaining to Rasul Ullah
and saying that the men are fighting Jihad(جهاد) and we are not.
So you can see that the customary meaning that they had of Jihad(جهاد) here, is what??
Fighting!! Because women are not prevented from Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس).
Why would the woman go and complain to Rasool Allah ﷺ
unless they understood what Jihad(جهاد) meant,
you go out and you fight the enemies of Allah.
So they complain to Rasool Allah ﷺ about that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded by saying
that your Jihad(جهاد) is Hajj(حَجْ).
So over here you'll find that the Rasul Ullah is using Jihad(جهاد) in
what?
Majaz(مجاز) meaning.
So for the women, your Jihad(جهاد) is Majazi(مجازی) and that is Hajj(حَجْ) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), when he was Khalifah(خليفه).
He received a letter from Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح).
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) stands up on the Mimber(ممبر) and he says:
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) is inviting you to Jihad(جهاد).
He didn't specify what type of Jihad(جهاد),
he just said: Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) is inviting you to Jihad(جهاد),
and Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) sent him this letter from the front line.
So the meaning was clear,
the speaker and listener exactly knows what the word means
- there's no confusion in their minds whatsoever.
Ali Bin Zaid(علي بن زيد), who's from the later times,
he is narrating a statement by Abu Talha(أبوطلحة).
He said: Talha(طلحة) says,
ٱنفِرُواْ خِفَافًا وَثِقَالًا
Go out light and heavy,
- young and old,
and then he said:
I don't see any excuse for anyone.
After this Ayah(آية), I do not see that any one of you is excused.
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) said:
And then he went out on Jihad(جهاد),
and that was the end of his statement,
he went out on Jihad(جهاد).
So the narrator, the meaning of Jihad(جهاد) is clear,
A man came to Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري),
when he was in the Masjid(مسجد), he said: O Abdullah bin Qais(عبد اللہ بن قیس),
If I were to pick up my sword and make Jihad(جهاد) for the sake of Allah.
And then I'm killed, where will I be?
Abu Musa(أبوموسى) said: In Jannah(جنة).
So the man is saying: If I pick up my sword and I go out in Jihad(جهاد), which is... the meaning is clear.
So this is the customary meaning.
The technical meaning of Jihad(جهاد)
among the scholars of Aqeedah(عَقِيدة), scholars of Fiqh(فقه), scholars of Hadith(حديث)
is also fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
If we look at some of the status of the fuqha(فقهاء).
In Hanafi(ألحنفي) in Al-Inaya Sharhul hidaya(ألعناية شرح الھدایة)
it says, that Jihad(جهاد) is calling towards the true religion and fighting with one soul and wealth
against those who reject it.
Al-Shirazi(ألشيرازي) in Al-Muhazab(المھذب)
which is Shafie(شافعی) book very brief, Jihad(جهاد) is fighting.
ألجهاد هو القتال
Full stop.
In Al-Maliki(ألمالکی) book
مواهب الجلیل فی شرح مختصر الخلیل
It says Jihad(جهاد) is a Muslim waging war against a non Muslim,
who has no peace agreement with the Muslims
and the fighting is for the sake of the word of Allah to prevail.
Jihad(جهاد) is also fighting the non Muslim who attacks, Muslim territory.
And it is also the Muslims, attacking the non Muslims in their land.
So this is the definition in
مواهب الجلیل فی شرح مختصر الخلیل
Which is a Maliki(مالكي) book.
Just simply look at the table of contents
in any book of the Salaf(سلف),
a book of Fiqh(فقه)
and you see the chapter of Jihad(جهاد).
Open up the chapter and see what it's talking about.
It's only talking about fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
the heading on the chapter would be Jihad(جهاد),
and then it goes straight on to fighting - Al-Qital(القتال).
For example, some of the books, in  Arabic that I looked up just to sample.
Al-Mughni(المغنی) by Ibn Qudamah(القدامة),
Al-Umm(الام) by Imam Shafie(امام شافعی),
Al-Mudawanna(المداونة) by Imam Malik(امام مالک).
The three commentaries on Al-Mukhtasir Al-khalil(المختصرالخلیل) by Kharshi(الخرشی) and
Ulaish(علیش) and Khattab(خطاب).
Al-Muhallab(المھلب) by Ibn Hazam(ابن حزم),
Subul Us-Salam(سبل السلام) by Sunani(صنعانی),
Nail-Al-Outar(نیل الاوطار) by Shoukani(شوکانی),
Al-Fatawa Al-Kubra(الفتاوة الکبری) by Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه).
The chapter that's talking about fighting they call it the chapter of Jihad(جهاد).
They didn't call it Qital(قتال), they said: Jihad(جهاد),
the meaning was clear to them.
Not only that,
whenever you want to cross a Hadith(حديث),
whenever you run cross a Hadith(حديث),
that uses the term Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Ibn-e-Hajar Al Asqalani(إبن حجرالعسقلانی) says:
Whenever Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is used in Hadith(حديث)
- it means Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So whenever you come across a Hadith(حديث)
and it says: Whoever does this in Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
- It means Jihad(جهاد).
And this is the statement by Ibn-e-Hajar Al Asqalani(إبن حجرالعسقلانی).
Some examples of that.
Salman Farsi(سلمان فارسي) said:
The messenger of Allah said:
Being stationed in the path of Allah for a day.
So here you have the path of Allah,
Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) means the path of Allah or in the cause of Allah,
that's how it is translated in English.
Whoever is station Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), for a day
is greater than fasting, the days of a month and praying it's night.
And if he dies his rewards of the deeds he used to do,
would continue and his provisions would continue
and he would be spared the trials of the angels of the grave.
In At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), there is a Hadith(حديث) by Abdullah Ibn Amr(عبداللہ ابن عمرو),
he says the Messenger of Allah said:
Two eyes will not be touched by hellfire
an eye that cries from the fear of Allah,
and eye that spent the night in a guarding post in the path of Allah.
So, if according to the other interpretation that Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) means everything.
Why would you need to guard?
Why would you stand and guard,
if Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) means anything.
So it necessarily means fighting.
Another Hadith(حديث) narrated by Nisai(نِسائ), Al-Hakim(ألحاكم), At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ) and Abu Dawood(ابوداؤد),
Amr Bin Absa(عمرو ابن عبسة) said:
We were laying siege to At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
And I heard the Messenger of Allah say,
Whoever shoots an arrow Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
will be rewarded like one, who has freed the slave.
Now shooting arrows can only mean fighting.
Some other terminologies
we might just define now,
we will talk about them a bit more,
when we come across them,
Ar-Ribat(الرباط),
Rabata(ربطه) means to tie something,
Rabata(ربطه) means to tie something.
When you tie your camel to a post.
When you tie anything, it’s Rabata(ربطه).
And it is used, the Shariah(شريعة) meaning of it,
is being in an outpost, being in an outpost.
An area where there's a possibility of an attack by the enemy.
So the land of Ribat(رباط) is the frontier land,
the lands of Ribat(رباط) is the frontier land.
So Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) was the land of Ribat(رباط).
Why? Because that was a frontier with the Romans.
AI-Iskandariyah(اسکندریة) was a land of Ribat(رباط) for some time.
Andalus(اندلس) was a great land of Ribat(رباط) for 800 years,
because there was always a front between the Muslims and the Romans.
So Ribat(رباط) is being stationed for the purpose of Jihad(جهاد).
The land of Ribat(رباط) is the land that is under threat of attack by the enemies of Islam.
The one, who is stationed the Ribat(رباط) is called The Muribat(مرابط).
And there was a great movement in our Islamic history, called Al-Murabitoon(ألمرابطون).
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) this is an amazing movement.
This was a movement of Shyookh(شیوخ), scholars
who were teaching among the Berber tribes of North Africa.
And they established Arbita(اربطة), places of settlement
on the frontier strip with non-Muslim Africa.
So whenever they are not studying ilm(علم)
they are fighting the enemy of Allah,
or making Da'wah(دعوة), so they combined between Da'wah(دعوة),
ilm(علم) and Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
The most idealistic life that you could ask for,
Da'wah(دعوة), ilm(علم) and Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
They would either be fighting the enemy or studying the books under the knees of scholars,
or making Da'wah(دعوة) to the non-Muslim tribes in Africa.
And it was because of this movement that Islam in Spain continued for a few centuries,
because the Muslims in Spain have reached to a level of decay,
where it was hopeless,
for them to fight against the Crusaders,
and they had to get help from who? From Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون)!
Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد),
who was the head of Seville(سويل) and this was at the time of a Tawaif(طوائف),
that was when Spain has broken up into small city states.
Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد) was being threatened by Al-Fonso(ألفانسو),
he had two options,
either to seek help from a Christian king,
or to seek help from Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون).
His advisors and other kings were telling him:
Do not seek help from the Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون) because if they come in,
they are not gonna get out.
Don't bring them up from Africa,
seek assistance from a Christian King.
Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد)
he had a wonderful reply he said:
I would rather be a shepherd of camels with Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين),
then be a shepherd of pigs with Al-Fonso(الفانسو).
He said: Even if he's going to come and stay and turn me into a shepherd for his camels.
That's better than being a shepherd of the pigs of Al-Fonso(الفانسو).
And he called in Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين).
Now Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد) he took a very good stand,
but Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد) in his own lifestyle
he lead a very flamboyant, lifestyle
he had 6000 concubines with their servants.
And his Palace I had a chance to visit his palace, it's just amazing,
the Palace of Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد).
Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين) when he came and saw how he is living.
Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين), he went around and he said:
Is this is how Al-Mutamid Bin Abbad(ألمعتمد بن عباد) lives every day?
Is this how his life is?
Because Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين) was described,
Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين) was a scholar and a Mujahid(مُجَاهِد),
and when he came to Spain,
he would live on camel milk, and barley bread,
and that was it and he had his tents from camel hair rope.
And he had a very simple lifestyle.
Yusaf Bin Tashfeen(يوسف بن تاشفين) was described by the ones,
who saw him, they said: He was tight as a watar(وتر)
you know the bow, the line of the bow, it's very tight.
So they say: He is as tight as a bow, when you look at his facial expressions, his muscles,
very tight, he wasn't spoiled by the luxuries of life.
So he was wondering, how Al-Mutamid(ألمعتمد) is living?
They say, this how he lives every day, they said: Yes! This is his daily life.
So this is the movement of the Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون).
The great movements in our history.
Ghazoo(غزؤ), linguistically means in pursuit.
Ghazoo(غزؤ) means in pursuit of something,
and it is used in Islamic terminology to refer to pursuing the enemy, in order to fight them.
So Ghazoo(غزؤ) is mostly when you attack the enemy in their land.
It's used more for Jihad At-Talab(جهاد ألطلب) rather than Jihad Ad-Dafah(جهاد ألدفعة).
You have two types of Jihad(جهاد),
Defensive Jihad(جهاد) and offensive Jihad(جهاد)
usually Ghazoo(غزؤ) is used to refer to, the offensive.
But you could also use it, for defensive.
We're done with the introduction so we can take a break
and then move on to the chapter one, we'll take some,
In Sha Allah(إن شاءالله) if you have any questions or comments.
After you milk the camel, the Hadith(حديث) says:
فواقة الناقة ، فواقة الناقة
After a camel is milked it takes some time for the breast
to gather milk for you to be able to milk it again.
The time between the two milkings is called fawaq(فواق),
which is, if we assume that the infant camel would suck in every few hours
than it would be one two three hours, something like that.
That is one meaning, the other meaning that I came across
is, it's the actual time it takes to milk a camel.
But, the stronger opinions is that, is the time between the two milkings,
the time between the two milkings of a camel,
which is a few hours.
So, fighting Jihad(جهاد) for a few hours, grants the person in Jannah(جنة).
The fastest ticket to paradise.
And it's one way.
Question from audience:
Yes! He does. He talks about four types of Jihad(جهاد).
Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس)
Jihad Bil Munafiqeen(جهاد بالمنافقین)
Jihad Bish-Shaytan(جهاد بالشَيْطَانْ) and Jihad Bil Kuffar(جهاد بالکفار).
Its talks about the four.
The concept itself of Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس) is valid concept.
But it's invalid to say that Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس) is
greater than Jihad Bil Kuffar(جهاد بالکفار).
That's what the problem is.
So, there is something called Jihad An Nafs(جهاد بالنفس),
which is a very broad meaning.
However it is not greater than Jihad Al-Kafireen(جهاد ألكافرين).
Jihad Al-Kafireen(جهاد ألكافرين) is Zarwat-Sanamal-Islam(ذروۃ سنامة السلام)
it's the highest peak of islam
Question from audience:
The command of the Jihad(جهاد) came in the same format
as a command to fast.
کتب علیکم الصیام ، کتب علیکم القتال
Fasting was prescribed on you, fighting was prescribed on you.
Now if somebody starts practicing Islam.
Do you tell them that we have to take you through an intensive Tarbiah(تربيعة) program before you fast.
You have to wait for 14 years,
until you are ready to fast.
We don't! How come we have this double standard when it comes to Jihad(جهاد).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ when the Jew came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, Mukhaireeq(مُخيريق)
and that is in the battle of Uhud(أحَد)
and he embraced Islam on the spot.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, join the ranks of the army.
He fought, and he died.
And he never prayed even one single Raka'a(رکعة).
I mean, this is a Jew, he is brought up as a Jew,
he needs a lot of Tarbiah(تربيعة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
مُخَیْرِيْق خیر الیهود
Mukhaireeq(مُخيريق) is the best of the Jews.
He goes straight to Jannah(جنة) without praying any Rakah(رکعة),
without doing anything, without zikr(زكر),
without Salah(صلاة) - nothing.
And that's why the Scholars say that the only deed
that does not have any prerequisites is Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
Shahadah(شَهَادَة) is sufficient in itself to grant the person
the high level in Jannah(جنة), he doesn't need anything before that.
So the whole issue of this Tarbiah(تربيعة) thing, I mean
one wonders where did it come from?
You need a lot of preparation, where does it come from?
It's not in the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ it's not in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) in the battle with the Romans,
he was running out of the Sahabah(صحابه).
So what he did, is he had to recruit
from the Arab tribes who are new Muslims.
So they came to Madina, all these recruits they came to Madina.
And these had no Tarbiah(تربيعة) whatsoever,
Yani(يعني) they had the rudeness, they had the roughness of the tribesmen,
and the Sahabah رضی اللہ عنھم have been brought up by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
good Akhlaq(أخلاق), good manners, so they were finding it difficult
getting along with these people.
And it was causing some problems in Madina,
so Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) stands up on the Mimber(ممبر) and he says:
I asked you in the name of Allah.
If I have any rights over you, being a Khalifah(خليفه),
that if any one of these people harm you.
Do not seek to punish them,
except if it is something that reaches the Hadd(حدّ).
And then he said: These people are going to be the
soldiers,who will fight your enemy and their harshness will be against your enemy.
The harshness, will be against your enemy.
So isn't it better for the sake of Allah to leave them and forgive them,
they said: Yes! He said: Then I asked you the name of Allah, to overlook their mistakes.
And this also another indication that the Mujahideen(مجاهدين),
the people should protect their honor.
And when they make mistakes because of what they're doing
one should be more forgiving towards them.
Because of the fact that their harshness, their rudeness whatever is against the enemy of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
not to approve their mistakes, but to overlook and to be forgiving.
The reason why I brought this up is to say that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
did not put these people to special training until they are,
they reach a level of the Sahabah(صحابه) in order to get in Jihad(جهاد)
immediately, just go and fight.
Question from audience:
The land of Ribat(رباط) is a Muslim land
but it's under threat of attack by the enemy.
If somebody is positioned in the enemy's land,
they would be a Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) not a Murabit(مرابط).
Cross Question from audience:
What do you mean?
As long as he's guarding.
Yes! Tayeb(طيِّب),
the issue of Bughaa(البغاء) whether that classifies as Jihad(جهاد) or not.
There are two opinions.
The Qital(قتال) of Bughaa(البغاء) does it qualify as Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) or not?
That issue, we have two opinions.
Even though it's the Qital(قتال) that carries Ajar(اجر) with it,
but is it Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) or not?
So the Murabit(مرابط) is somebody who is guarding the
- guarding the Muslim land from attack by the non Muslims,
or by Muslims, who would be allied by the Kuffar(كفار).
So, now it's not Bughaa(البغاء) anymore but it's Muslims who are aligning themselves with the Kuffar(كفار).
Question from audience:
Bughaa(البغاء), are the people of Baghi(بغي), who would revolt against the Muslims
who are following Bid'ah(بدعة), and they're fighting for it.
So they are Muslim, but they are against the Sultan(سلطان).
Question from audience
Well there was Al-Muwahidoon(ألموحدون),
but Al-Muwahidoon(ألموحدون) were not
as pure as the movement of Al-Murabitoon(المرابطون).
Al-Muwahidoon(ألموحدون), they had some problems,
but they tried to emulate the same example of Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون).
But then you do have for example, with
one needs to do more study about this,
but within the subcontinent, you have people like Shah Jalal(شاه جلال)
and you have, like, Ahmed Irfan(أحمدعرفان) Shaheed(شَهِيد),
these are movements of scholars and students
who are ever in Ribat(رباط) in Jihad(جهاد)
But the Yani(يعني) the most, famous movement of all is Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون),
because of the extent of their rule.
I mean, they controlled a huge part of Africa,
that included Algeria, Tunisia,
Libya, Morocco, the, the desert south of Morocco,
Mali, Senegal, Niger, Nigeria, that whole western coast of Africa
was under Al-Murabitoon(مرابطون), and then Spain.
It was a huge Islamic State.